Abdul Aziz

PhD Researcher,
School of Communication, Digital Media researcher Centre (DMRC)
Queensland University of Technology (QUT), Australia
Z9 Building, Level 6, Kelvin Grove QLD 4059
azizabdul.mcs@gmail.com, a5.aziz@hdr.qut.edu.au

Professional Summary:

I studied media, communication and development studies and conducted research related to ICT policy, digital divide, ICT4D, social inequality, sexuality and cultural diversity, South Asia/Bangladesh. I'm interested in shaping and contributing to projects that involve themes of digital culture and social justice in the context of multicultural and marginalized communities. Being a multilingual (e.g., Bangla, English, Arabic, Rohingya dialect) gives me the advantage of being able to speak to a range of people and my "insider" and "outsider" role allocates for rich and indepth analysis.

Work experiences

Research scholar (PhD), (July 2019-Present), School of Communication, Digital Media Research Centre (DMRC), QUT,

- Conduct research on digital media use and digital transformation from a societal perspective
- Writing research proposal and planning for research project
- Write articles and journal papers for publication in high quality journal and present research outcomes in meeting, seminars and conferences

Project Coordinator, (Nov 2018-June 2019) Centre for Inclusive Society and Development, Dhaka

- To maintain and monitor project plan, budgets and schedules.
- To document updated all required materials needed for stakeholders and partners

Community and Knowledge Manager (Internship), (July-Sep 2017), WorldLoop, Brussels, Belgium

- To transcribe technical content into visually attractive and data mining of common issues.
- To develop a knowledge platform to leverage technology and social media platforms and update all required digital materials for International donors and partners.

Journalist/ Correspondent (February'14-May'15) Daily New Age & Asian Age, Dhaka, Bangladesh

• New gathering, report writing, interviewing, news editing

Research Assistant, (April-December 2013), World Vision, Bangladesh

• data collection to assess livelihood and everyday lives of readymade garments' women workers in Chittagong city, Bangladesh.

Education:

Ph. D School of Communication.

Queensland University of Technology (QUT), 2019-present

M.A. Digital Communication Leadership (DCLead), 2016-2018,

Vrije University Brussels (VUB) Belgium, Salzburg University (SU), Austria. Specialisation: Digital communication, Policy and Innovation in Europe | Thesis: ICT Policy Challenges for Digital Inclusion in Bangladesh: Evaluating Policy and Practices

MSc. Management of Development.2015-2016

VHL University of Applied Sciences, Netherlands
Specialisation: Social Inclusion, Gender and Youth | Thesis: Social exclusion of Hijra and official recognition in Bangladesh

B.A. Communication & Journalism, University of Chittagong, Bangladesh, 2008-2012

Certificate Courses

- Leadership and Communication (2020), e-Grad School, Australia
- Project management (2020), e-Grad School, Australia
- Filmmaking and TV Journalism for Peace and Tolerance (2014)

Awards/Scholarships:

- QUT Postgraduate Research Award (2019-2022), Queensland University of Technology (QUT)
- Erasmus Mundus Scholarship (2016-2018), European Union located in Brussels, Belgium.
- Netherlands Fellowship Program-NFP (2015-2016), NUFFIC, The Netherlands.

Affiliations/Membership:

- Digital Media Research Centre, QUT, Australia
- Association of Internet Researchers (AoIR)
- Emerging Scholars Network, UNSW Law, Australia
- Erasmus Mundus Association (SA Chapter), Belgium
- Holland Alumni network, Nuffic, the Netherlands
- Centre for Inclusive Society and Development (CISD), Bangladesh

(

Professional interests/fields

- Media, communication & cultural studies
- Digital divide, inclusion, ICT policy
- Media, migration & diaspora
- Race/ethnicity, identity & religion/Islam
- South Asia/Bangladesh
- Qualitative research methods

Publications:

ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4817-8556

Peer-reviewed

Naima, U., & Aziz, A.(2021). Banking without Interest: Customers' Perceptions on Religiosity and Financial Inclusion through Islamic Banking. *Under review*

Aziz, A., & Naima, U. (2021). Rethinking digital financial inclusion: Evidence from Bangladesh. *Technology in Society*, *64*, 101509. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.techsoc.2020.101509

Aziz, Abdul. Digital inclusion challenges in Bangladesh: The case of the National ICT Policy. *Contemporary South Asia* 28, no. 3 (2020): 304-319. https://doi.org/10.1080/09584935.2020.1793912

Abdul Aziz & Sameena Azhar (2019). Social Exclusion and Official Recognition for Hijra in Bangladesh. *Journal of Research on Women and Gender*, 2020, Vol. 9,3-19.

Opinion/Commentary & Review

Aziz, Abdul, Mohammad Morshedul Islam, and Muhammad Zakaria. COVID-19 exposes digital divide, social stigma, and information crisis in Bangladesh (2020). *Media Asia*, 47, 3-4:144-151. https://doi.org/10.1080/01296612.2020.1843219

Aziz, A. (2020). Rohingya diaspora: Transnational identity in the digital age. *The Diplomat*.

Conference presentations

"Renegotiating transnational familyhood: Affects, temporalities and the politics of mobility regimes", *The virtual 71st Annual International Communication Association Conference*, May 27-31, 2021 <u>ACCEPTED</u>,

[https://www.icahdq.org/page/ICA2021]

"Digital media, faith and conflict: Reimagining religious space for ethnic identity formation among Rohingya diaspora", *Religious Identity and the Media (Methods, concepts, theories, and new research avenues)*, March 25-27, 2021. Warsaw, Poland, ACCEPTED [https://media.religion2021.uni-bremen.de/WordPress/]

"Researching diaspora in the digital age: new directions towards a transnational approach", 7th Biennial ACSPRI Social Science Methodology Conference, December 1-3, 2020 [https://conferences.acspri.org.au/2020/talk/VJSC3L/]

"Rohingya Diaspora: Identity and Integration in the Digital Age", *Emerging Scholars Network Annual Workshop*, (Asia-Pacific research group), Andrew & Renata Kaldor Centre for International Refugee Law, UNSW, 10th-13th November 2020 [https://kaldorcentre.unsw.edu.au/]

"ICT Policy Challenges for Digital Inclusion in Bangladesh: Evaluating Policy and Practices." *ICA 2020 Preconference*, *Digital Cultures of South Asia: Inequalities Infrastructures, Informatization*. May 21, 2020, [https://www.icahdq.org/mpage/CFPDigital]

"Social exclusion Official reignition of third gender in Bangladesh", *Gender Equality Norms and The Politics of Development Cooperation*, May 18-20, 2016, Danish Institute for International Studies (DIIS), Denmark, [https://www.diis.dk]

Documentary (digital production)

- Why did she choose to be a farmer? (2015), Wageningen, the Netherlands. This film portrays young women entrepreneurs in agriculture in the Netherlands with a comparative perspective of Indonesia and Nigeria. This documentary film used observational and reflexive approaches of course of Media Design for Social Change at VHL University of Applied science, the Netherlands.
- Language for Peace (2014), Dhaka Bangladesh. The film explores different indigenous identities are progressively getting lost due to the strong predominance of the Bengali language. The project was a part certificate course by UC SanDiego and Qualcomm Institute, the USA.

References:

Dr Michael Dezuanni

Associate Director, Digital Media Research Centre (DMRC) Professor, School of Communication Queensland University of Technology (QUT), Brisbane Australia m.dezuanni@qut.edu.au

Mohammad Zakaria

Associate Professor Dept of Communication & Journalism University of Chittagong, Bangladesh zakariacu@gmail.com